你好,学生
hello students
我是Yan
I'm Yan
今天我们继续
and today we're going to continue
关于Linux进程的基础系列
on our fundamentals series with Linux process run time
前面我们看了一个程序/bin/cat
so previously we looked at how a program /bin/cat
但实际上是我们为了方便，写的自定义的cat
but really our custom version of cat that we wrote for simplicity
是如何加载的
gets loaded
从像磁盘上的elf二进制文件那样的程序
goes from being a program like an elf binary on disk
到进程虚拟内存空间的程序
to being a program in the virtual memory space of a process
好了，我们谈谈下一步吧
all right let's talk about the next steps
在加载完成，初始化后
so after it's loaded initialized etc
就开始执行了
execution begins
这是如何处理的，执行是如何开始的
how is that handled how does execution begin
它是用__libc_start_main函数来处理的
well it is handled using a function called __libc_start_main
它是一个库函数，你的二进制文件会调用它
it's a library function that your binary will call
然后它会调用你的main函数
and expect that to call your main function
这个过程有点曲折
it's a bit of a convoluted process
它这样子的原因有很多
for a number of reasons this is the way it is
我们快速看一下
but let's take a quick look
我展示一下，然后接着往前
so I can show it to you and then you will move on
上个视频中的示例我还开着呢
oops I still had this open from a previous demo
好了
so all right
我们快速看一下我们的cat
let's look at our cat program real quick
简单明了
nice and simple
只有一个main函数
just has a main function that
cat会打开给定文件或标准输入
cats have either file or standard in
这取决于是否给了它参数
depending on whether arguments were given to it or not
当然，如果你记得这里
of course if you recall right here
这是个检查
this is a check
只要给了参数
if any arguments were given
一定是有argv[0]的
there will always be argv[0]
正常情况下
I mean normally
你当然可以用空的argv启动进程
you can of course launch a process with a completely empty argv
默认情况下，argv[0]里放的是程序名
by default your shell will put argv[0] as the name of the process
或者是启动程序的命令（如python）
or the name of whatever command was invoked to end up running that program
如果argc是2或者更多
otherwise if argc is you know two or more
这意味着有argv[1]
that means there is an argv[1]
argv数组里的第二个元素
a second argument in that array
此时可以打开一个文件来读
and it'll be able to open a file for reading
好的
all right
开工吧
let's roll
当我执行cat时，就像刚刚做的那样
when I execute cat as I just did up here obviously
它输出了这个文件
it cats out the file
但这个执行过程是怎么开始的
but how does that execution actually happen
我创建了一个用于LD_PRELOAD的库
I created a little tiny library that will be able to LD_PRELOAD
它能替代__libc_start_main
to grab a hold of __libc_start_main
在这之前
actually before we do that
我展示一下
let me show you
如果用readelf看一下cat
if we do readelf on the cat binary
你看这里
and you look right here
这个10c0是程序的入口地址
this 10c0 is the entry point address of the program
加载器（解释器）会来这里执行
right so this is where the loader will redirect execution
程序加载地址 +0x10c0
wherever it loaded plus 10c0
当然，这是在加载器加载完cat依赖库等东西后
after it is done loading libraries and everything the cat depends on
我们看一下这个位置有什么
let's take a look what is there at that location
如果用objdump反汇编cat
so if we use objdump to disassemble cat
每次我都忘了用正确的汇编语法
and every time I forget to do it in the right assembly syntax
请记住
remember
在x86架构上，用英特尔汇编风格
when on x86 use Intel assembly
因为AT&T的汇编风格看起来很别扭
because AT&T assembly just looks weird
就是这个
here it is
这里是_start
we have our start right there and
等一下
wait a second
鼠标光标失控了
my mouse cursor just went crazy let me
好了，start在0x10c0
okay we have start right here at 10c0
然后是
and then we have
一系列设置操作
after a bunch of setup
这里用汇编指令call调用了__libc_start_main
we see an assembly call into __libc_start_main
然后__libc_start_main接管执行流
and then __libc_start_main takes over execution
我们看看
let's take a look at
编译
compile
我说过我们有个
so I mentioned we have our little
这是另一节课的东西
that's from a different thing
抱歉，有点不在状态
sorry it's been a long day
看看这个
take a look at this
我写这个是为了展示
I wrote this guy to showcase
能通过LD_PRELOAD替换 __libc_start_main
that we can LD_PRELOAD __libc_start_main
和其它库函数一样
just like we can any other library
所以编译肯定没问题
so we can of course compile this
现在执行cat时，可以加上LD_PRELOAD start_main.so
now we can LD_PRELOAD start_main.so when we do cat
它输出了hello
it just types hello
我们再看一遍
we look at again
看看写的代码
we look at what we wrote
它覆盖了__libc_start_main
it overwrites __libc_start_main
这是__libc_start_main的参数
this is the arguments that __libc_start_main takes
都是比较特别的东西
it's some crazy stuff
一个指向main函数的函数指针
it takes a function pointer to main
你应该非常熟悉C中的函数指针
you should get very familiar with this function point syntax in C
这个参数名叫main
this is a argument called main
它是一个函数
which is actually a function
它接收3个参数
which takes 3 arguments
int型的argc
int argc
char**的argv
char** argv
还有char**的envp
and char** envp
我们稍后会讨论envp
and we'll talk about envp in a sec
还有参数
it takes an argument to
实际的argc
the actual argc
实际的argv
the actual argv
这是一堆用于初始化的函数指针
a bunch of function pointers to initializers
像构造函数，析构函数等等
constructor destructors and so forth
还有一个指向栈底的指针
and a pointer to where the stack ends
我不清楚它是如何获得环境变量指针的
I have no idea how it gets the environment variable pointer
我没深入调查
I didn't look into it
我这里直接传入了0
so I just passed that 0
然后直接调用了main
but then we just call main
很酷
very cool
所以当你LD_PRELOAD时
so when you LD_PRELOAD
它做的就是
all it does
输出个你好
prints hello
然后用main的返回码做退出码
then exits with the return code
而且这行得通
and it works
很酷
cool stuff all right
所以我们甚至可以覆盖这么基础的功能
so we can overwrite even this sort of base functionality
好的，我们继续
all right let's move on
下一步是什么?
what is next
cat在启动后
so cat after it gets launched
会从内存中读取参数和环境变量
it reads its arguments and environment from memory
有两个参数argv和envp
we have these two arguments argv and envp
我们看看这能拿到什么
let's look at what that entails right
程序启动时，来自外部的唯一输入
again the only input from the outside world at program start
就是这些参数
are these arguments
其他的就是加载到内存中的二进制文件本身
everything else is just binaries loaded in memory
什么是环境变量
what is actually an environment variable
我们来看一看
let's take a look
环境变量
an environment variable
是LD_PRELOAD之类的东西
is something like this LD_PRELOAD thing
它本质上就是个参数
it is an argument essentially
通过argv这组字符串参数之外的途径，传给程序的参数
an extra argument that you can pass outside of the argv set of strings to your program
有很多环境变量
there's a lot of environment variables
你可以用env
you can hit env
列出此时所有的环境变量
to list out all the environment variables set for you at that time
这里有很多
there's a lot of them here
如果你想的话，也可以编程查看
if you want of course you can ask them programmatically
我写了一个小的env
I wrote a little env
这是个系统工具
actual system utility
我写了一个替代品
I also wrote a little replacement for it
方便我们玩一玩
for us to play with
先获取这个envp
you get this envp
然后遍历
and you can just iterate through
输出envp的各个条目
and print out every entry of envp
直到遇到终止envp数组的空指针
until you hit a null pointer that terminates the envp array
编译一下
so let's compile this
好的，运行它
okay and run it
漂亮
boom nice and simple
我们也可以传入环境变量
all right we can also pass it some environment variable
在这里，它出现在了envp中
and here it is it shows up in our envp
我也可以
I can also
这
so this
让我
let me just
这可以让我传入多个环境变量
this lets me just send tons of environment variable
或者说给它加入多个环境变量
or add tons of variables to its environment
用空格分隔
separated by spaces
如果希望在环境变量中使用空格
if you want spaces in your environment variables
你可以这么做
you can do this
简单明了
nice and simple okay
环境变量是传递参数的好方法
environment variables are good way to pass arguments to
例如，往LD_PRELOAD中的用于调试的库传参
for example little LD_PRELOAD libraries you designed to debug things
因为很难拿到当时实际的命令行参数
because it's a pain in the butt to grab the actual command line arguments at that point
环境变量还能改变你熟知工具的行为
they also changed the behavior of some normal utilities that you might be used to
我创建了这个test目录
so I created this test folder
在这个test目录中
inside this test folder
有五个文件
there are five files
分别叫1、 a、A、b、B
files called 1、 a、A、b、B
执行ls -l
do an ls -l
它会根据文件名排序
it sorts the files by name
这里的结果看着很合理
and here we have something that looks reasonable
1、a、A、b、B
但有趣的是
but the interesting thing is
在ASCII中，大写字母应该排在小写字母之前
in ASCII the upper case letters should go before the lower case letters
A为0x41
A upper case is 0x41
B为0x42
and B upper case is 0x42
a是0x61, b是0x62
a lower case is 0x61 and b is 0x62
所以应该是用了别的配置
so they should be very differently configured
事实证明
it turns out that
是因为这个默认设置的LANG环境变量
this LANG environment variable that's set by default is responsible
这会告诉libc
this tells libc
可能libc
probably libc
不是libc就是ls
either libc or ls
用别的方法对这些文件排序
to sort these file names differently
如果我们将LANG设置为C
if we set the lang to capital c
表示C语言
c the language
这是ASCII的排序方式
this is the default like ASCII normal way of sorting it
然后可以用ls -l看一下排序结果
then we can do ls -l and see the correct sorting so to say
就是举个例子，说明环境变量有影响
just as an example that these variables have impact
好的，我们讨论完了环境变量
all right we have talked about variables
我们继续
let's move on
cat能从环境中获取环境变量
so cat gets its variables from the environment
一切都很好
everything is all super happy of course
但它也需要和外界保持互动
it needs to keep interacting with outside world
不只是一个单向的
it's not just like a one way
不是说给它一堆参数，然后它自己做就好了
we just give it a bunch of arguments and does a thing
它需要能打开文件之类的（和os交互）
it needs to be able to open files etc etc
它是怎么做到的呢
so how does it do that
程序是如何实现它们的功能的
how do programs actually achieve their functionality
特别是当这个功能特别复杂的时候
when that functionality can be pretty complex
从范式的角度来说
well one kind of way paradigm speaking
就是说，使用库函数
in terms of like paradigms is using library functions
实际上，在你的一生中，应该努力
you should actually in your entire life strive to write as
写尽量少的代码
little code as possible
尽可能少写几行代码
few lines of code as you possibly can
你可以用库函数实现这个目的
and you do that by using library functionality
聪明点，学用库
be smart about it and use libraries
库
libraries
我们得费一番周折才能找到库
we have to go through a whole crazy thing to even find where the libraries are
就像上节课讲的那样
as we talked about in the last lecture
现在我们需要更进一步
now we need to go through a further thing
要找到用的库中某个函数的地址
to understand where in the library certain functions are that we're using
这些被称为符号
these are called symbols
就像二进制文件中的一些名字
as in like names of the binary
我们快速看一下
so let's take a quick look
我要说的是
I'm gonna mention
我主要会讲历史背景中的这个过程
I'm mostly talking about this kind of in a historical context
这曾经有
this used to be a massive surface of like
一个巨大的攻击面
a massive attack surface
因为过去可以改动进程的加载过程
because you used to be able to really mess with the loading process
现在基本不行了
recently this is not really the case anymore
过去，符号都是在要用的时候解析
it used to be that all of these symbols would be resolved on demand
比如，你的程序用了printf
so if your program used printf
不会一开始就找到printf在libc中的位置
printf wouldn't actually be located inside libc
只有在马上要调用printf时，才会找
until you went and called printf
这是因为，一个复杂的程序
this is because of a complex program
可能用了成千上万的符号
that used maybe thousands and thousands of symbols
而且运行的电脑也慢
and was loaded on a slow computer
把这些都查一遍要花些时间
would actually take a while to look all of these up
所以只想等用时，再费工夫
and you don't want to pay that cost until you actually use that functionality
现在我们的电脑速度非常快
nowadays our computers are blazing fast
而这种用时才查找的方式，有很多安全问题
this on demand lookup caused so many security problems
出了很多安全漏洞
and exposed so many security holes
所以我们通常不这样做了
that we no longer normally do that
现在符号解析都很快，且安全
nowadays things mostly get resolved at low time and protected
我们将在内存错误模块，讨论曾经的符号解析方式
so we'll actually revisit this in the memory corruption section from a historical perspective
但现在，我就展示一下二进制文件中的符号
but for now I'm just gonna show you what symbols look like in a binary
然后就继续往下
and then we'll move on
我们的cat在这里
alright so we have our cat
我们看一下cat导入的符号
let's look at the symbols that cat imports
这些是cat用到的各种库函数
so these are all of the various library functions that cat will use
当然不只是函数，也可以是库导出的全局符号
or not just functions that can also be globals exported by the library
这里有__libc_start_main
you know __libc_start_main
当然还有，open read write
of course we use open read and write
这个，这是一个安全机制，将在内存错误中讨论它
this is a security feature we'll talk about in the memory corruption module
这基本上防住了特定类型的攻击
that basically protects against certain expectation types
这些是其他的
these are various other
抱歉
sorry that
这些是其它的一些构造和析构的功能
these are various other functionality set up and tear down
这些是cat导入的全部符号
and these are all the symbols that cat imports
cat导出的符号
the symbols that cat exports
有_start，这是入口地址
are _start that's where our entry point is
看看能不能找到main
let's see if you can find main
main在这里
here's main
很酷
pretty cool stuff
我们还可以看看start_main库的符号
we can also look at our start_main library
它更有趣
that's more interesting
它导出了__libc_start_main
it actually exports __libc_start_main
它在哪里
where is that
在这
there it is
它导出了__libc_start_main
it exports __libc_start_main
但如果你再看看cat
whereas if you look at cat again
只看导入符号
just just the import
它导入了__libc_start_main
it'll import __libc_start_main
我用的是nm
I'm using nm
它是查看二进制文件里符号的工具
it's a utility to look at symbols in binaries
粗略地讲
roughly speaking
这些标记着U的符号
these symbols that are U
不是在该二进制文件中定义的
that are not defined in the binary
会从其它文件导入
will be imported from somewhere else
二进制文件中定义了的，有地址的符号
symbols that are defined in the binary that have an address
就有可能导出给别的文件
will be potentially exported somewhere else
现在，如果我们用file查看cat
in fact nowadays if we look at cat using file
正如我在上一讲中提到的
as I mentioned earlier in the previous lecture
现在
nowadays
所有这些动态链接的二进制文件
all these dynamicly-linked binaries
它们实际相当于自己的库
they are actually libraries of their own
能把cat当库放到LD_PRELOAD中用
I could LD_PRELOAD cat in
这可能会造成一些混乱
that will probably cost some chaos
因为将会有2个main函数
because there would be two main functions
但理论上，你可以把cat当成库加载
but you know theoretically you could load cat as a library
这无关紧要
that's neither here nor there
我们继续吧
let's get back to work
现在我们看了库函数
so now we've looked at library function
它是一种与环境交互的方法
so that's one way of interacting with the environment
另一种方法是什么
what is another way
我们还能怎么做呢
how else might we do it
我们还可以用系统调用
well we do it using system calls
我们在上个视频中，已经提到过2个了
we already mentioned two previously in the process loading
fork、clone，实际还有第三个execve
fork clone and actually a third execve
这些都是系统调用
so these are all system calls
这是你与Linux操作系统交互的方法
this is how you interact with Linux as an operating system
与外部世界交互的方法
with the world like all external interaction is going to be
至少要通过系统调用来启动
at least going to be initiated through system calls
我们可以用strace
we can use strace
这个我们已经在加载的视频中见过了
which we already kind of a sneak peak in the loading
用它查看执行时调用的系统调用
to look at these system calls as they execute
我们来看一下
so let's check it out
我们strace cat cat.c
let's say strace cat cat.c
你可以看到具体发生了什么
so you can see exactly what happens
从起初的execve
starting from the execve
然后进入各种初始化过程
and going onwards into various setup procedures
比如为库映射虚拟内存之类的
you know mapping in space for libraries and so forth
一直到打开我们想输出的文件
all the way through opening the file we want to cat out
读取这个文件
reading that file
这是我们读到的内容
so this is what is read
读取了170字节
read a 170 bytes
如果我们检查一下这个文件的大小
and if we actually check how big that file is
正好是170字节
it is exactly 170 bytes
然后把它写出来
and then writing it out
我们在这里执行的write
so here we do the write and
大小是170字节
with a 170 and of course the
这是
this is
strace在标准错误输出，输出系统调用
the strace prints out the system calls to standard error
而二进制文件在标准输出，输出东西
while the binary is printing stuffs to standard out
它俩都输出到一个终端
because it goes to the same terminal
所以我们都能看到
so we can
哦，不是这个
oops wrong one
我们可以重定向输出
we can redirect the output
现在看起来更清爽了
and now this looks a little cleaner
或者可以重定向标准错误输出
or we can redirect standard error
只看标准输出
and just see the original output
好的，我们执行了read
alright so we do the read
然后write
we do the write
又read了一次，返回结果为0
we do another read and we get 0
然后我们退出
and then we exit
如果我们看一下cat.c，就懂了
if we look at cat.c that makes exact sense
这是那个while循环，表示
so here's the while loop says
在read时，read的返回值大于0
while we read our read returns greater than 0
并且write的返回值大于0
and the write returns greater than 0
就保持循环
keep looping
这里，read返回值为0，就终止了循环
in this case the read returned 0 and we terminated
好了
there you go
这就是系统调用
that is system call
还有一件事
one more thing
如果你执行 man syscall
if you man system call
能看到很多关于系统调用原理的文档
this will give you a whole lot of documentation about how system calls work
这是它们在不同架构上的调用约定
this is how their calling convention on different architectures
很酷
it's very cool stuff
你还可以单独查看某个系统调用
you can also look at a specific system call
比如，open
this is open for example
这是它的文档
with its documentation
你能看到，我没include很多东西
you'll notice that I don't include stuff
导致这里很多警告
and this leads to warnings everywhere
我懒
I'm very lazy
但man手册能告诉你要include什么
but you know man page will tell me what to include
就可以解除这些警告
so that the warnings go away
这很好，但我不会去做
which would be awesome but I'm not gonna do it
好吧，很酷
all right cool
还有一件事
one more thing
你在C中使用的这些系统调用
these system calls that you use in C
它们实际就是被调用的C函数
they're actually C functions that get called
如果我们反汇编cat，然后看main
so if we disassemble cat and we look at main
它调用了libc中的open
it's calling open inside libc
不自己写汇编代码，很难让libc
it's very hard without writing custom assembly to actually get libc to
或让gcc显示触发系统调用的代码
or to get GCC to emit code that triggers a syscall
因为libc有很多封装
libc has wrappers for it
它们会触发对应的系统调用
that will trigger the correct system call
如果你不想用libc
if you don't want to use libc
想写不用libc的代码
if you want to write code that doesn't use libc
你在shellcode模块某个作业中，写shellcode时
when you're writing shellcode in one of your assignments in the shellcoding module
你需要手动触发系统调用
you will need to handcraft those system calls
一个很好的系统调用资源是
one awesome resource for system calls is
怎么更好的展示呢
how can I show this easily
我会把它放到对应的模块里
I'll post it in the module instead alright
酷
cool
所以
so
你还可以调用syscall
you can also do a syscall call
它能让你指定号码，来调用系统调用
which allows you to specify the system call number
每个系统调用对应了一个号码
each system call has a number
我们用strace时
so as we strace this
我们实际能看到
what we would actually see
strace的输出太友好了
because strace is too friendly
每个系统调用都有一个号码
every system call has a number
触发一个系统调用，实际上是
and what happens to trigger a system call
我们将在shellcode模块中更详细地讨论这个
we'll talk about this actually more in the shellcoding module
传入这个号码，就触发了对应的系统调用
is you pass that number and you trigger a system call
为了展示给你看
to show you
我搜一下系统调用号
let me look up the system numbers
好的
all right
比如，read的系统调用号是0
for example read is system call zero
所以我们可以修改cat.c
so we can actually modify cat.c
不用read了
instead of read
改用syscall 0 加上参数
we use syscall 0 with the argument
好的
okay
编译cat.c
compile cat.c
执行cat cat.c
cat cat.c
用上strace
do the strace
效果看起来一模一样
and looks exactly the same
write系统调用号是1
write is syscall 1
所以我们可以这样
so we can do this here
这让我们更接近
this gets us one step closer
原本的样子
to what things would look like
如果你在shellcode中手动用汇编调用系统调用
if you were writing syscalls manually in assembly in shellcode
我们稍后再做最后一步
and we'll take the final step there a little later
让我
let me
怎么展示呢
how would I show you
我在哪里看到的系统调用号表
so where I get the syscall numbers
哦，你可以在这边上看到
oh you can see it here on the side
放在了最右边
but it is actually optimized for the slide
你应该看不清
so you can't really see it
这是一个由Ryan A. Chapman创建的Linux系统调用表
this is a Linux syscall table created by Ryan A. Chapman
他是所有shellcoder的英雄
he is a hero of shellcoders everywhere
你可以搜索Ryan A. Chapman x86系统调用表
you can just Google Ryan A. Chapman x86 syscall table
非常有用
very useful all right
回到幻灯片
back to slides
我们继续
let's roll on
这就是系统调用的工作原理
so that's how syscalls work
这是与环境互动的唯一方式吗
is that the only way to interact with environments
用系统调用
I mean using syscalls
我们可以做很多很多事情
we can do many many many things
我们可以open、read、write、fork、execve
we can open read write as we saw fork execve
可以用wait来等待子进程终止
we can use wait to wait for a child process to terminate
实际上，我们必须使用它来避免僵尸进程
we actually have to use it to avoid zombie process
我马上就会讲到它
that I'll talk about in a sec
我们可以调用任意的系统调用
we can invoke arbitrary syscalls
有的系统调用能让进程作为调试器，附加到别的进程
there are syscalls to attach to process as a debugger
有的能打开网络链接
there are syscalls to open network connections
有很多不同的系统调用
there are syscalls for quite a lot of various things
可以用man syscall查看更多信息
you can again look at man syscalls for more information
非常标准的操作系统接口
very standard interface for doing operating system stuff
一般来说
generally speaking
要在Linux中做任何事情
to do anything in Linux
你必须打开某种资源，然后与之互动
you have to open some sort of resource and then interact with it
使用read和write
using read and write
有时还有其它的系统调用
sometimes other syscalls other times
我们将在内核模块中进一步探讨这一点
we will explore this even further in the kernel module
好的
all right
系统调用是一种调用进os的方法
syscalls are a way to call into the OS
但当发生某事时，os不能这样进到你的进程
but the OS can't invoke a syscall into your process when something happens
os该如何向你发声
how can the OS talk to you
或者说，外面的进程如何向你发声，引起你的注意
or someone externally talk to you and kind of to get your attention
当然，你可以用系统调用
of course you can use syscalls to
不断读一个管道或文件，检查读到的数据
like read from a pipe constantly and check or read from a file
但另一种方法是信号
but another way is to use signals
信号就是信号
a signal is a signal
基本上就是OS给你的进程打了个招呼
basically a hey that the OS sends to your process
有很多不同种类的信号
there's a bunch of different signals
你可以为其定义信号处理程序
that you can define signal handlers for
你也可以发信号给别的进程或自己
and you can send to other processes or yourself
如果你没有某个信号的处理程序
if you don't have a signal handler for a signal
当你接收到这些信号时
and you receive one of these signals
会采取默认的处理行为
the default action will be taken
对于某些信号，默认行为是忽略
for some signals the default action is ignore
其他的，则是退出
for others it is die
你的进程将会退出
your process will die
有两个信号是无法捕捉的
there are two signals that cannot be caught
一个是SIGKILL
one is SIGKILL
所以如果你在Linux中执行kill -9 某个进程
so if you ever kill -9 something in Linux
你这是在给目标进程发送信号9
that is what you're doing you're sending it signal 9
二是SIGSTOP，信号19，它会把进程放到后台
and SIGSTOP signal 19 it'll background a process in Linux
有趣的是，SIGSTOP有两种
interestingly there are two variants of SIGSTOP
信号19、信号20
signal 19 signal 20
在shell中按ctrl z，发送信号20
when you hit control Z in your shell it sends signal 20
这个信号可以被捕获
which you can catch
这挺烦的
which is really annoying
信号19的话，你必须手动发送
signal 19 you have to send manually
这是些常见的信号
all right this is kind of the common signals that you'll see
SIGINT是按ctrl c时发送的
SIGINT is what is sent when you hit control C
SIGQUIT，我记得大多数终端都是按ctrl 反斜杠(\)
and I think SIGQUIT for many terminals is control backslash
还有很多其他的
various other ones
如果你的某个子进程停了，会收到SIGCHLD
you can have a signal  if one of your children processes has stopped
调整了终端窗口大小的话
with your terminal windows resized
这个没列出来
that's not listed here
也会发送个信号
but that sends a signal to the shell
很酷
all sorts of cool stuff
我们快速看一下信号
anyways let's take a quick look at signals
我写了个程序能捕捉所有信号
so I wrote a crazy thing that catches all signals
这个循环会遍历所有信号
so this loops through all of the signals
然后用这个函数，为每个信号，登记信号处理程序
and it registers a signal handler using this signal function
这个函数就是输出收到的信号量
and the signal handle just only prints out that
收到信号后，啥也不做
it received the signal and does nothing
然后这个程序就一直在这里循环
and then this thing sits there and loops forever
这是个很让人无语的程序
it's a very frustrating program
因为很难让他退出
because it's very hard to kill
如果我按Ctrl C，它就输出收到信号量2
if I hit Ctrl C it says got signal 2
我们稍后再看，但要是kill -l一下
we'll look later but if you do kill -l
能看到信号量2是SIGINT
it'll tell you signal 2 is SIGINT
按ctrl z，是信号量20 (SIGTSTP)sig terminal stop
control Z there's signal 20 (SIGTSTP)sig terminal stop
很难关掉这个程序
it's just hard to kill this program
现在我在另一个终端
in another terminal right now
执行这个kill -9
I'm gonna do this kill -9
我们先执行-19 SIGSTOP
actually let's do -19 first SIGSTOP
然后跟着 pgrep signal
and then this guy pgrep signal so that
现在我把它复制粘贴到另一个终端
so I'm gonna copy that paste it into another terminal
好的
boom
现在我们关了这个程序
so now we have stopped this binary
你可以用bg（口误）
and bg you can bg
看这个列表
this list
下面列出了后台信号
this list the background signals
它收到的信号18是什么
what is signal 18 that it got
哦，抱歉
oh bg sorry
jobs是用来列出当前进程的
jobs is how you list the jobs that are currently around
bg是用来把进程放到后台
bg is to send a job into the background
然后恢复运行
and resume its running
让它在后台恢复运行
resume running a process in the background
bash把后台进程称之为jobs
jobs is what bash calls these background processes
如果执行kill -l
if you do kill -l
我们看一看
let's take a look
我打赌18是SIGCONT
I bet 18 is SIGCONT
是的，18表示，你现在可以继续执行了
yep so 18 says hey you're now continuing
因此，它触发了处理程序，然后恢复执行
so it triggers the handler and then resumes execution
它现在在后台运行
so it's running in the background
你可以用fg把它切回到前台
you can hit fg to bring it back to the foreground
当然，现在我们又遇到了同样的问题
and now of course we're stuck with the same problem
此时我再发送19
when I send this kill 19 again
jobs看一下
jobs
现在它在后台，停了
now it stopped in the background
我们看看
let's see
当它在前台运行时，会收到窗口变更信号吗
in the foreground will it get the window yeah
看，信号28
see signal 28
好的，现在我要恢复直播画面
okay but now I need to fix my stream okay
酷，收到了多次信号28
awesome got signal 28 many times
如果我们在另一个终端停掉它
if we stop it again in a different terminal
信号28是SIGWINCH（WINdow CHange）
signal 28 is SIGWINCH window changed
有很多酷的信号
so there's a lot of cool signals
当你正在写入的文件的文件描述符失效时，会收到信号
there are signals that happen when a file descriptor you're writing to has stopped working
比如，连接中断之类的
there are like connection drop or whatever
程序遇到了段错误，也会收到信号
when your program segfaults that's a signal
这个接收所有信号的例子程序中，没有段错误
so this program that catches everything is unsegfaultable
不管怎样，这很有趣
anyways that's fun and all
我们来关了它
but let's kill it
不能直接关
we can't do that
所以要执行kill -9 $(pgrep signal)
so what I'm gonna do is kill -9 pgrep signal
signal是程序的名字，pgrep的作用是
that's the name of the binary all pgrep does
我再暂停一下
actually let me pause it again
pgrep会告诉你进程的id
pgrep just tells you its process ID
它和
it's the same as
哦
oops
和这个差不多
roughly the same as doing this
这是我系统在后台升级
that's my system upgrading in the background
这个是我们的signal程序
and then here's our signal guy alright
现在它停在后台
so it is stopped in the background
如果我们把它放到前台
if we foreground it now
再kill -9
I'm gonna do kill -9
关掉了
boom killed that
没办法捕获kill -9或kill -19
no way to catch kill dash 9 or kill dash 19
这就是信号
that is signals
很酷
very cool stuff
你可以用信号做些很酷的事
using signals you can do some cool stuff
比如，再讲一个
you can for example one more thing
我快速写个示例程序
I'm gonna write you a program real quick
马上回来
I'll be right back
好的，我回来了
all right I am back
看一下我刚写的程序
let's take a look at this program I wrote for you
这是一个有用的信号
this is a useful signal
闹钟信号14
alarm signal 14
kill -l看一下
so if you do kill -l
就是这个
here it is
SIGALRM
beautiful SIGALRM
当然，要是我在代码中include kill.c
of course if I had included kill.c
我就可以用这个宏了
I could actually use this macro
但这个不碍事
but we're gonna rough it out
我们就用实际的信号值
tough it out and use the actual signal number alright
方便你记住
so that you can remember
信号14是个告警
signal 14 is alarm
这有一个alarm函数
there's a function called alarm
它能为某个信号设置告警
it sets an alarm clock delivery for a signal
它告诉内核
so it tells the kernel hey
它是个系统调用，它告诉内核
it's a syscall it tells the kernel hey
在这里是，3秒后给我个信号14
give me signal 14 in 3 seconds in this case
或是多久后
however many however long
看起来它只支持秒
looks like it only supports seconds
可能有其他细分系统调用支持纳秒之类的
probably there's a way syscall to support nanoseconds or whatever
默认情况下，收到信号14，进程会退出
by default receiving signal 14 will kill your process
它会先输出文字提示，然后关闭进程
it'll actually print alarm clock and kill your process
我们要改变它
we're gonna change it
我们在这里捕获到它
we're gonna catch it here
输出DING
and print ding
然后退出
and then exit
你可以做别的
you can do anything
不必退出
you don't have to exit
有个重要的事情
it's a great thing
我马上会讲，就是
an interesting thing I'll show you in a sec is that
接收到一个信号
receiving a signal
能让你从某个代码块中跳出来
breaks your program out of certain block situations
比如从sleep状态跳出来
like a long sleep
我们编译
so we compile
运行
we run
它在这个死循环中，等3秒
it's gonna wait three seconds in this infinite loop
我们
let's
它会在这个死循环中等三秒
gonna wait three seconds in this infinite loop
然后会触发警报
and then the alarm will trigger
然后执行这个信号处理函数
it'll hit this signal handler right here
输出DING，然后退出
printing and exit all right
好的
awesome
运行
run
2 1
叮
Ding boom
酷，我改一下
awesome so let me show you another cool thing here
如果我们不退出
if we don't exit
当然，它会继续运行
of course this will keep running
一直循环下去
it'll just keep looping
我展示一下
let me just show you that
1 2 3
还接着运行
keeps running
这种持续运行的方式很蠢
this is a silly way to run forever
因为这浪费了很大力气
because it puts a lot of strength
你的CPU一直在运行
your CPU is just running constantly
相反，可以sleep很长一段时间
instead you can sleep for a very long time
这是10万秒
this is 100 thousand seconds
但
but
哦
oops
1 2 3 boom
程序退出了
it terminated
所以有一些系统调用是可以被信号打断的
there are certain system calls that are interruptible by signals
我想，类似的
I think in a similar way
如果我们从标准输入中读取数据
so if we do read from standard in
但不输入任何东西
and don't give it anything
我猜也能被打断
I think we should also be able to interrupt that
我们试一下
let's test
我错了
I was wrong
read不会被alarm打断
so read doesn't get interrupted by an alarm
好吧
all right
重点是
point is
有其他方法能让read超时
there are other ways to make read time out
但这太深入了
but that's going off on way too deep attention
我还是改回去吧
let me just undo that
这是原来的alarm
so we have our old alarm binary file
好的，这就是信号，我们不继续深入了
cool that's signals we're now going to move on
另一种交互方式是共享内存
another way of interacting with the outside world is shared memory
有多种方法可以与另一个进程建立共享内存
there are various ways to establish shared memory with another process
最简单的一个方法是
the easiest one
有方法是通过clone实现的
there are ways to do it through the clone syscalls
但用fork是不行的
one way that you cannot do it is with fork
fork很有趣，它会分裂
fork very interestingly actually splits
会先拷贝内存再写
makes the memory regions copy and write
当进程想往里写的时候
whenever a process tries to write to it
它会先复制一份内存，再往拷贝的自己的内存中写
it'll actually just copy it and write to its own private version
但有其它方法
but there are other ways
有个目录/dev/shm
there's a file system that exists in /dev/shm
我给你展示一下
let me show it to you
很多东西用了这个
this file system is used for a bunch of stuff
我机器上没有
well not on my machine
它基本就是一个内存映射的文件系统
but it's basically a memory mapped file system
你可以在这里创建文件
you can create files here
再用mmap映射这些文件
and map these files using mmap
你可以在不同进程中，用文件描述符映射它
you can map a file by its file descriptor from multiple processes
然后同时访问它
and access it at the same time
可以把它当作一种建立共享内存的简单方法
and use this as an easy way to set up shared memory
很酷
very cool
设置共享内存
set up shared memory
很简单
super simple
这是一种与外界交流的方式
and it's a way to communicate with outside world
或者把共享内存用到别处
or with other things using that shared memory
好吧
all right
我们已经走到了尽头
we've come to the end
现在该发生什么了
what happens now
cat要终止了
cat terminates
终止不是很重要
termination is surprisingly not so trivial right
进程只有一两种终止方式
termination in a process can handle one or two ways
收到一个没有处理函数的信号
receiving an unhandled signal
或者调用exit系统调用
or calling the exit system call
这是进程结束的唯二方式
those are the only two ways that a process conterminated
你可能会说
you might say
要是遇到段错误了呢，进程崩了呢
oh but what about a segmentation fault if my process crashes
猜猜段错误是什么？信号
guess what segfault is a signal
当进程崩溃时
when your process crashes
实际上是它收到了一个信号
what actually happens is it receives a signal
信号10
signal 10 and
让我
let me
不知道为啥，有点不确定
now for some reason I just had a moment of doubt
不是信号10
no of course not signal 10
是信号11
it's signal 11
我在说啥，累了累了
what am I saying it's been a long day
它收到信号11，段错误，然后崩溃
it receives signal 11 the segfault and crashes
说错了，不是崩溃
and not doesn't crash
它收到信号11，进程终止
it receives a signal 11 and terminates
因为没有处理函数
because it doesn't handle it
你可以为信号11，注册个信号处理程序
you can install a handler for signal 11
让进程在段错误后，继续运行
and survive seg faults
你甚至可以尝试修复问题，再继续运行
you can even try to fix things up and keep going
但这通常是个坏主意
but that's generally a bad idea
你也可以给其它没崩溃的进程发送信号11
you can also send a signal 11 to other processes that didn't crash
你可以用kill发信号
that you can you know send kill signals to
让它们没出错时，报段错误
and make them segfault without them doing anything wrong necessarily
但不管怎样
but anyways
这是Linux中仅有的2种终止方法
these are the only two ways to go in Linux
退出后
after you go after you exit
或者说被杀死后
or you get killed
进程必须被接收
your process must be reaped
所以进程终止后
so after a process terminates
它会进入僵尸状态
it'll remain in a zombie state
直到它的父进程接收到它
until its parent waits on it
如果不wait你的子进程，就终止了
if you don't wait on your children processes and you die
子进程会重找一个父进程
they will be reparented
并一直保持僵尸状态
and will remain zombies
这以前是个大问题
this used to be a big problem
因为直到最近，Linux进程ID才只有16位
because until very recently Linux only had 16 bit integer for its process ID
所以可能会用完进程ID
so you could actually run out of processes
但现在它是32位整数
now it's a 32 bit integer and
很难用完它
it's much harder to run out of processes
但这总归不好
but still not good
执行ps aux时，会看到一大堆僵尸进程
you do ps aux and you see a ton of zombies
它们是那些括号括起来的
they're the ones in parentheses
不好看
not fun
所以要接收你的子进程
so reap your processes
用wait系统调用接收它们
use the wait system call to collect their status
好的
all right
就是这些
and that is it
我们讲完了Linux进程的全部生命周期
we have gone through the entire life cycle of a Linux process
我录了好几次
it has taken me dozens of tapes
我头几张PPT总出问题
I kept screwing up in the first couple of slides
然后重录
and then kept restarting
用了好几个小时了
it's been hours
我现在又渴又饿
I am thirsty and hungry
超级累
super tired
谢谢你的坚持
thank you for sticking with it
我们后面的课程再见
I will see you in future lectures
再见
good bye